Guide to the John W. Burton papers, 1937-1988
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
John W. Burton papers
1937-1988
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
John W. Burton, 1915-
C0006
9 linear feet (17 boxes)
The John W. Burton papers contain materials from Burton's work in international relations including correspondence, working papers, notes, news clippings, and scholarly publications. It also includes materials pertaining to the creation of the George Mason University Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution (ICAR).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by John Burton and Betty Nathan in 1989-1995.
Biographical Information
John W. Burton was born on March 2, 1915 in Melbourne, Australia. He was educated at Newington College, Sydney, the University of Sydney, and the London School of Economics. Burton's early career was marked with academic as well as diplomatic success. He was part of the Australian delegation sent to San Francisco after World War II to set up the United Nations. He became the youngest Permanent Secretary of the Australian Diplomatic Service and was appointed High Commissioner in Ceylon, but resigned to seek elected office.
In 1954 Burton's career focused increasingly on academics. During this time he published his first book on foreign policy titled The Alternative. In 1963, he moved to England to teach at the International Relations Program at University College, London, where the Centre for the Analysis of Conflict was originally set up. Over the next twenty years, Burton published many books on the subject of diplomacy and conflict resolution.
Burton and the original Centre for the Analysis of Conflict moved to the University of Kent at Canterbury in 1979 where he remained until 1981. He then moved to the University of South Carolina where he was awarded an International Studies Association Fellowship. After a brief but productive period at the University of Maryland, Burton was persuaded to join George Mason University to help in the development of a new Centre for Conflict Analysis and Resolution, now known as the Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution (ICAR).
Scope and Content
The John W. Burton papers contain materials from Burton's work in International Relations including correspondence, working papers, notes, news clippings, and scholarly publications. It also includes materials pertaining to the creation of George Mason University's Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution (ICAR).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject and topic.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds records and publications from the Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution.
Index Terms
Persons:
Burton, John W. (John Wear), 1915-
Corporate Names:
George Mason University. Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution.
Subjects:
Conflict management.; International relations.; Middle powers.
Contents List
- JOHN W. BURTON COLLECTION
  - " WORLD ORDER AND THE MAP OF PEACE " (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - " CONFLICT RESOLUTION - PROCESS OR ANALYSIS " (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - " NORTHERN IRELAND: CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - " CONFLICT RESOLUTION AS PROBLEM SAVING AND THE RULE OF THE THIRD PARTY " (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - " THE THEORY OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - " THE PHILOSOPHY OF PUBLIC POLICY " (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - " DISCOVERY IN CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - " THE TEACHING OF POLITICS " (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - " ASSESSMENT OF DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS " (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - " CONFLICT RESOLUTION WORKSHOPS AS TEACHING SITUATIONS " (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - " NEUTRALITY AND NON ALIGNMENT " (Folder 11, Box 1)
  - " SOME NOTES ON JOHN BURTON 'S PAPERS ON 'RESOLUTION OF CONFLICT' " (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - " EVOLUTION THAT NEARLY WENT WRONG " (Folder 13, Box 1)
  - " THE NATURE OF WORKSHOP " (Folder 14, Box 1)
  - " THE NATURE OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 15, Box 1)
  - " AN APPROACH TO ECONOMIC POLICY AND TAXATION " (Folder 16, Box 1)
  - " THE INTERNATIONAL FACILITATING PROCESSES " (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - " MAPPING THE FIELD OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 18, Box 1)
  - " CONFLICTS OF INTERESTS: SUBJECTIVE OR OBJECTIVE ? " (Folder 19, Box 1)
  - " THE NATURE OF AGGRESSION AS REVEALED IN THE ATOMIC AGE " (Folder 20, Box 1)
  - " THE CENTER FOR INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS: DIRECTORY OF FELLOWS " (Folder 21, Box 1)
  - " THE COUNCIL FOR THE FACILITATION OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT RESOLUTION: THE FACILITATING PROCESS " (Folder 22, Box 1)
  - " READINGS IN PEACE AND CONFLICT " (Folder 23, Box 1)
  - " REFLECTIONS ON SWADHYAYA " (Folder 24, Box 1)
  - " NECESSITOUS MAN AND CONFLICT RESOLUTION " (Folder 25, Box 1)
  - " UNIVERSITY PRESS OF AMERICA: RESOLVING DEEP-ROOTED CONFLICT " (Folder 26, Box 1)
  - " PERSONALITY TYPES AND POLITICAL DECISION MAKING: BRIDGING TROUBLED WATERS " (Folder 27, Box 1)
  - " METHODOLOGY AND DEVELOPMENT ", [JOHAN GULTANG] (Folder 28, Box 1)
  - " A CRITICAL ASSESSMENT OF THE POWER OF HUMAN NEEDS IN WORLD SOCIETY " (Folder 29, Box 1)
  - " JUVENILE UNEMPLOYMENT AND JUVENILE DELINQUENCY " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - " THE FACTS OF THE BANDUNG CONFERENCE " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - " THE LIGHT GROWS BRIGHTER " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 3, Box 2)
  - " REGIONALISM ,FUNCTIONALISM AND THE UNITED STATES " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 4, Box 2)
  - " THE RIGHTS AND OBLIGATIONS OF NONALIGNMENT " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 5, Box 2)
  - " DISARMAMENT AND ARMS CONTROL, REGIONAL DISARMAMENT :SOUTH-EAST ASIA " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 6, Box 2)
  - " DISARMAMENT AND ARMS CONTROL: ESCAPE FROM POWER " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - "THE EVOLVING INTERNATIONAL SYSTEM ,FRONTIER(VOLUME 7)" 1937 - 1969 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - "PEACE RESEARCH AND INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - " INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS IN 1984, NEW SCIENTISTS(VOLUME 22,NO.394) " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - " THE DISTINCTIVE DISCIPLINE " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - " OUR GENERATION AGAINST NUCLEAR WAR(VOLUME 3): UNILATERALISM AS A PROCESS 1937 - 1969 (Folder 12, Box 2)
  - " THE END OF THE PACIFISTS DILEMMA " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 13, Box 2)
  - "INTRODUCTION:REVUE INTERNATIONALE DES SCIENCES SOCIALES " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 14, Box 2)
  - "CONFLICT AS A FUNCTION OF CHANGE " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 15, Box 2)
  - " WESTERN INTERVENTION IN SOUTH-EAST ASIA " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 16, Box 2)
  - " THE DECLINING RELEVANCE OF COERCION IN WORLD SOCIETY " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 17, Box 2)
  - " MEDIATION RECONSIDERED " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 18, Box 2)
  - " UNIVERSAL VALUES AND WORLD POLITICS ",INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL 1937 - 1969 (Folder 19, Box 2)
  - " NONALIGNMENT AND CONTEMPORARY WORLD POLITICS " 1937 - 1969 (Folder 20, Box 2)
  - " NO-ALINEACION Y POLITICA MUNDIAL CONTEMPORANEA ", ESTUDIOS INTERNACIONALES (VOLUME 3,NO.1) 1937 - 1969 (Folder 21, Box 2)
  - " OBSERVATIONS ON INTERNATIONAL NEGOTIATIONS " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - " TEACHING ABOUT COLLECTIVE SECURITY AND CONFLICT". THE SYSTEMS APPROACH 1971 - 1976 (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - " RESOLUTION OF CONFLICT " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - "SOME FURTHER COMMENTS -IN REPLY TO CRITICISM ",INTERNATIONAL STUDIES QUARTERLY (VOLUME 16,NO.1) 1971 - 1976 (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - " THE ASSOCIATION OF DIRECTORS OF SOCIAL SERVICES ", PROCEEDINGS OF THE FIRST STUDY CONFERENCE 1971 - 1976 (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - " A TOTAL ENVIRONMENT ", THE NEW ERA(VOL 53,NO.8) 1971 - 1976 (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - " THE END OF THE ICE AGE ", MEANJIN QUARTERLY 1971 - 1976 (Folder 7, Box 3)
  - " THE END OF AN ICE AGE?, A LETTER TO RUSSEL WARD", MEANJIN QUARTERLY 1971 - 1976 (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - " POUR UNE APPROCHE SYSTEMIQUE DES RELATIONS INTERNATIONALES",(ENGLISH VERSION ALSO) 1971 - 1976 (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - "THE STUDY OF WORLD SOCIETY: A LONDON PERSPECTIVE " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - "THE KOREAN JOURNAL OF INTERNATIONAL STUDIES(VOL.6,NO,2), ALTERNATIVES TO CONFRONTATION :NORTH-SOUTH KOREAN RELATIONS " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - " JOURNAL OF INTERNATIONAL STUDIES (VOL.4,NO.3):THEORY AND REALITY " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - " JOURNAL OF INTERNATIONAL STUDIES (VOL.5,NO.1):DYNAMICS OF CHANGE IN WORLD SOCIETY " 1971 - 1976 (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - " JOURNAL OF INTERNATIONAL STUDIES (VOL.8,NO.1): THE ROLE OF AUTHORITIES IN WORLD SOCIETY " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 1, Box 4)
  - " NOTES OF MEETINGS AND DISCUSSIONS IN MOSCOW IN 1980 " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 2, Box 4)
  - "INTERNATIONAL CONGRESS OF ARTS AND SCIENCES UNIVERSAL NEEDS AND PUBLIC POLICIES: THE END OF IDEOLOGIES " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 3, Box 4)
  - "INTRODUCTION COMMENT TO PAPER :UNIVERSAL NEEDS AND PUBLIC POLICIES " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 4, Box 4)
  - " SYNTHESIS AND ANALYSIS " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 5, Box 4)
  - "THE ROLE OF INDEPENDENT STATES IN RESOLVING THE THERMO NUCLEAR PROBLEM " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 6, Box 4)
  - " RECESSION OR UNDEVELOPMENT?" 1979 - 1983 (Folder 7, Box 4)
  - "UNPUBLISHED DOCUMENTS ON PROBLEM SOLVING AS A MEANS OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1978 - 1982 (Folder 8, Box 4)
  - " WIN-WIN ,A MANUAL ON CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 9, Box 4)
  - " THE MIDDLE EAST BETWEEN RUSSIA AND AMERICA " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 10, Box 4)
  - "THE PHILOSOPHY OF DISPUTE RESOLUTION " SEPTEMBER ,1982 (Folder 11, Box 4)
  - " THE JORDAN CENTER FOR STUDIES AND INFORMATION " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 12, Box 4)
  - "FAIL SAFE :THE SECOND TRACK " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 13, Box 4)
  - "GREAT POWER CONFLICT RESOLUTION: LOOKING BEYOND CONVENTIONAL WISDOM " 1983 (Folder 14, Box 4)
  - " INTERNATIONAL PROBLEM SOLVING ORGANIZATION: A CONTINUING SEMINAR AND AN INTERNATIONAL FACILITATING SERVICE " APRIL, 1983 (Folder 15, Box 4)
  - " A SOVIET- USA SUMMIT " JUNE, 1983 (Folder 16, Box 4)
  - " THE PRESENT STATE OF SOVIET-AMERICAN RELATIONS: THE PERSONALITY PROBLEM " JUNE ,1983 (Folder 17, Box 4)
  - " CONFLICT AND CONFLICT ACCOMMODATION :SECURITY AND CHANGE " AUGUST ,1983 (Folder 18, Box 4)
  - " SOVIET-AMERICAN RELATIONS AND THE ROLE OF SMALLER STATES: THE SELF-FULFILLING NATURE OF THE INDUCTIVE THINKING " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 19, Box 4)
  - " MULTI-ETHNIC SOCIETIES: THE ZONAL SYSTEM " NOVEMBER ,1983 (Folder 20, Box 4)
  - " IS THERE A ROLE FOR SMALLER STATES IN CONTEMPORARY WORLD SOCIETY? " 1979 - 1983 (Folder 21, Box 4)
  - " THE SECRETARY - GENERAL AND SATELLITE DIPLOMACY " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 1, Box 5)
  - "NORTH AND SOUTH KOREA :SHARED AND SEPARATE VALUES", KOREA AND WORLD AFFAIRS (VOL.8,NO.1) 1984 - 1985 (Folder 2, Box 5)
  - " WAR AND IT'S PREVENTION " MARCH ,1984 (Folder 3, Box 5)
  - " PERSONAL PHYSICAL SECURITY IN CIVIL CONFLICTS, THE CONSEQUENCES FOR CONFLICT RESOLUTION " APRIL, 1984 (Folder 4, Box 5)
  - " SYSTEMS THINKING AND WORLD AFFAIRS " APRIL, 1984 (Folder 5, Box 5)
  - " THE FACILITATION OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT RESOLUTION " SEPTEMBER ,1984 (Folder 6, Box 5)
  - "THE HISTORY OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 7, Box 5)
  - " THE FACILITATION OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT RESOLUTION: THE FRUITS OF FAILURE " NOVEMBER, 1985 (Folder 8, Box 5)
  - " ABOUT WINNING " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 9, Box 5)
  - "CENTER FOR ELECTRONIC CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 10, Box 5)
  - "UNITED NATIONS UNIVERSITY " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 11, Box 5)
  - "KOREA " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 12, Box 5)
  - " NATIONS AND NEEDS (VOL.1) " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 13, Box 5)
  - "THE DOMESTIC SOURCES OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT: MANAGEMENT IMPLICATIONS " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 14, Box 5)
  - "TAX REFORM - A MISSED OPPORTUNITY ? ,RECESSION OR UNDEVELOPMENT " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 15, Box 5)
  - "THE HISTORY AND PRESENT STATE OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION ",FORUM FOR CORRESPONDENCE AND CONTACT (VOL.15,NO.2) 1984 - 1985 (Folder 16, Box 5)
  - " U.S.-SOVIET DIALOGUE AND CONFLICT RESOLUTION " DECEMBER ,1985 (Folder 17, Box 5)
  - "THE HISTORY AND PRESENT STATE OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION: RESPONSE TO DISTRUSTS ",FORUM FOR CORRESPONDENCE AND CONTACT (VOL.15,NO.4) 1984 - 1985 (Folder 18, Box 5)
  - " NATIONAL SECURITY AND REGIONAL SETTLEMENTS " 1984 - 1985 (Folder 19, Box 5)
  - " THE THEORY OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1986 (Folder 1, Box 6)
  - "U.S.S.R " 1986 (Folder 2, Box 6)
  - "CENTRAL AMERICA " 1986 (Folder 3, Box 6)
  - "THE ASIA FOUNDATION " 1986 (Folder 4, Box 6)
  - "THE ABC OF COMMUNITY LAW " FEBRUARY ,1986 (Folder 5, Box 6)
  - "RESOLVING REGIONAL CONFLICTS ",PEACE IN ACTION 1986 (Folder 6, Box 6)
  - " SOCIALIZATION,CONTROL AND CONFLICT RESOLUTION " MARCH ,1986 (Folder 7, Box 6)
  - "THE RECONCEPTUALIZATION OF DEVELOPMENT" MARCH ,1986 (Folder 8, Box 6)
  - "PEACE BUILDING AND THE UNITED NATIONS",[JUERGEN DEDRING] 1986 (Folder 9, Box 6)
  - "REPRESSION OR RESPONSE TO DEMANDS ?" MAY ,1986 (Folder 10, Box 6)
  - "WHAT TO DO ABOUT DISPUTES THAT ARE NON-NEGOTIABLE" JUNE ,1986 (Folder 11, Box 6)
  - "NEGOTIABLE AND NON-NEGOTIABLE ISSUES ",FORUM FOR CORRESPONDENCE AND CONTACT (VOL.16,NO.2) 1986 (Folder 12, Box 6)
  - "THE ROLE OF MIDDLE POWERS IN CONFLICT RESOLUTION " 1986 (Folder 13, Box 6)
  - "MIDDLE POWERS SEMINARS " 1986 (Folder 14, Box 6)
  - "THE MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: PURPOSE AND AGENDA" JUNE ,1986 (Folder 15, Box 6)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: INDONESIA " 1987 (Folder 1, Box 7)
  - "LETTERS OF INVITATION TO SEMINARS,UNITED NATIONS,FOR MIDDLE POWERS " 1987 (Folder 2, Box 7)
  - "OBJECTIVE POLITICS :THE SOURCES OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " NOVEMBER, 1986 (Folder 3, Box 7)
  - "A FRAMEWORK FOR PUBLIC POLICY" 1987 (Folder 4, Box 7)
  - "PUBLIC CHOICE,INTERACTIVE MANAGEMENT,CONFLICT RESOLUTION,PROBLEM SOLVING AND PUBLIC POLICY" 1987 (Folder 5, Box 7)
  - "THE ROLE OF MIDDLE POWERS IN CONFLICT RESOLUTION", A REPORT OF THE SECOND MEETING MAY ,1987 (Folder 6, Box 7)
  - "FISHER,RON AND KEASHLY " 1987 (Folder 7, Box 7)
  - "ELDERS COUNCIL OF INDIA " 1987 (Folder 8, Box 7)
  - "IRAN " 1987 (Folder 9, Box 7)
  - "THE WILLIAM AND FLORA HEWLETT FOUNDATION" 1987 (Folder 10, Box 7)
  - "ORGANIZATIONS OF AMERICAN STATES" 1987 (Folder 11, Box 7)
  - "EXPANDING THE DEBATE ON GENERIC THEORY",NEGOTIATION JOURNAL (VOL.3,NO.1) 1987 (Folder 12, Box 7)
  - "DEMYSTIFYING CONFLICT RESOLUTION " FEBRUARY ,1987 (Folder 13, Box 7)
  - " REPRESSION OF HUMAN NEEDS: SYSTEM SURVIVAL OR DESTRUCTION ?" MAY ,1987 (Folder 14, Box 7)
  - "PEACE INSTITUTE REPORTER INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT RESOLUTION PRIORITIES " JUNE ,1987 (Folder 15, Box 7)
  - "CONFLICT RESOLUTION AS A POLITICAL SYSTEM",COPRED PEACE CHRONICLE (VOL.12,NO.5) 1987 (Folder 16, Box 7)
  - "COURTS, ALTERNATIVES DISPUTE RESOLUTION AND CONFLICT RESOLUTION ", PEACE IN ACTION (VOL.3,NO.3) 1987 (Folder 17, Box 7)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: ORGANIZATIONS OF AFRICAN UNITY " 1987 (Folder 1, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE :LEAGUE OF ARAB STATES " 1987 (Folder 2, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: ARGENTINA " 1987 (Folder 3, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: BRAZIL " 1987 (Folder 4, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: CANADA " 1987 (Folder 5, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: COSTA RICA " 1987 (Folder 6, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: EGYPT " 1987 (Folder 7, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: FIJI " 1987 (Folder 8, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: FINLAND " 1987 (Folder 9, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE :FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY " 1987 (Folder 10, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE :GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC " 1987 (Folder 11, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: GREECE " 1987 (Folder 12, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: INDIA " 1987 (Folder 13, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: INDONESIA " 1987 (Folder 14, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: JAPAN " 1987 (Folder 15, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: MEXICO " 1987 (Folder 16, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: NIGERIA " 1987 (Folder 17, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: NORWAY " 1987 (Folder 18, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: PAPUA-NEW GUINEA " 1987 (Folder 19, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: POLAND " 1987 (Folder 20, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: ROMANIA " 1987 (Folder 21, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: SINGAPORE " 1987 (Folder 22, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: SPAIN" 1987 (Folder 23, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: TANZANIA " 1987 (Folder 24, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: VENEZUELA " 1987 (Folder 25, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: YUGOSLAVIA " 1987 (Folder 26, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE: ZIMBABWE" 1987 (Folder 27, Box 8)
  - " MIDDLE POWERS CONFERENCE " 1987 (Folder 28, Box 8)
  - "CONFLICT RESOLUTION,UNITED NATIONS,RESEARCH PAPERS " 1987 (Folder 29, Box 8)
  - " CIVILIAN DEATHS IN WARTIME " 1988 (Folder 1, Box 9)
  - " THE DANA McLEAN GREELEY FOUNDATION FOR PEACE AND JUSTICE, INC" 1988 (Folder 2, Box 9)
  - " A GENERAL MODEL OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT DYNAMICS " 1988 (Folder 3, Box 9)
  - " THE POLITICS OF PERSUASION ,IMPLEMENTATION OF FOREIGN POLICY: THE CASE OF THE NETHERLANDS " 1988 (Folder 4, Box 9)
  - "SEMINAR ON CONFLICT RESOLUTION :INTRODUCTORY COMMENTS" JANUARY ,1988 (Folder 5, Box 9)
  - "DEFINING THE FIELD: A SEMINAR " JANUARY ,1988 (Folder 6, Box 9)
  - "DEFINING THE FIELD OF CONFLICT ANALYSIS AND RESOLUTION " 1988 (Folder 7, Box 9)
  - "CONFLICT RESOLUTION AS A POLITICAL SYSTEM " 1988 (Folder 8, Box 9)
  - "UNOFFICIAL DIPLOMACY " FEBRUARY ,1988 (Folder 9, Box 9)
  - " METHODOLOGICAL ISSUES IN CONFLICT RESOLUTION " FEBRUARY ,1988 (Folder 10, Box 9)
  - "ISRAEL-PALESTINIAN SIMULATION" 1988 (Folder 11, Box 9)
  - "NOMINATION FORMS - JENNINGS RANDOLPH DISTINGUISHED FELLOW" 1988 (Folder 12, Box 9)
  - "A MARKOV MODEL OF FOREIGN POLICY ADAPTATION" 1988 (Folder 13, Box 9)
  - "ANALYTICAL PROBLEM-SOLVING CONFLICT RESOLUTION", AN EXPLANATORY PAPER 1988 (Folder 14, Box 9)
  - "PEACE IN ACTION (VOL.4,NO.1)" 1988 (Folder 15, Box 9)
  - "DIALOGUE ,DEAR MARGOT" MARCH ,1988 (Folder 16, Box 9)
  - " HUMAN NEEDS AND THE NEED FOR AN ENEMY" MARCH ,1988 (Folder 17, Box 9)
  - "UNDERSTANDING THE GLOBAL ARENA " MARCH ,1988 (Folder 18, Box 9)
  - " THINKING ABOUT FOREIGN POLICY: FINDING AN APPROPRIATE ROLE FOR ARTIFICIALLY INTELLIGENT COMPUTERS " 1988 (Folder 1, Box 10)
  - "A NEGOTIATING MODEL APPLIED TO THE PARIS PEACE CONFERENCE" 1988 (Folder 2, Box 10)
  - "ARE THE MORAL AND VALUE FOUNDATIONS OF MULTILATERALISM CHANGING ?" 1988 (Folder 3, Box 10)
  - "GROUP THINKING AND COGNITIVE COMPLEXITY IN BRITISH FOREIGN POLICY DECISION MAKING,DURING THE MUNICH AND POLISH CRISES" 1988 (Folder 4, Box 10)
  - "CONTINUITY AND CHANGE IN U.S.-IGO RELATIONSHIP: A COMPARATIVE ANALYSIS WITH IMPLICATIONS FOR THE FUTURE OF MULILATERALISM IN U.S. FOREIGN POLICY" 1988 (Folder 5, Box 10)
  - "COALITION LEADERSHIP IN GLOBAL WARS " 1988 (Folder 6, Box 10)
  - "THE TERRORISM ENVIRONMENT" 1988 (Folder 7, Box 10)
  - "STRUCTURING OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS: TESTING GALTUNG'S THEORY OF NORTH-SOUTH INFORMATION FLOWS " 1988 (Folder 8, Box 10)
  - "FOR THE CREATION AND DEVELOPMENT OF JOINT U.S.-SOVIET FACILITATION TEAMS TO RESOLVE CONFLICTS IN AREAS OF COMMON INTERESTS" MAY ,1988 (Folder 9, Box 10)
  - "HUMAN NEEDS AND DESIRES :WEST ,EAST AND SOUTH CHRISTIAN BAY " 1988 (Folder 10, Box 10)
  - "A FOUNDATION FOR A GENERAL THEORY OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION ? ", ABSTRACT- C.R.MITCHELL 1988 (Folder 11, Box 10)
  - "WHY NOT JOINT U.S.-SOVIET CONFLICT RESOLUTION TEAMS?",PEACE IN ACTION (VOL.4,NO.2) 1988 (Folder 12, Box 10)
  - " THE NEED FOR NEEDS THEORY " JUNE ,1988 (Folder 13, Box 10)
  - "LETTER RESPONSE ON WORLD CONCERNS",FORUM FOR CORRESPONDENCE AND CONTACT (VOL.18,NO.2) 1988 (Folder 14, Box 10)
  - "PROSPECTS OF A PALESTINE-ISRAEL SETTLEMENT " 1988 (Folder 15, Box 10)
  - "TRANSNATIONALISM AND THE BIRTH OF TRACK TWO DIPLOMACY ",JOSEPH V.MONTVILLE 1988 (Folder 16, Box 10)
  - "THE SECURITY DILEMMA AND PEACE PARADOX: INSIGHTS FROM BEHAVIORAL AND POST-BEHAVIORAL TRADITIONS " 1988 (Folder 17, Box 10)
  - "NEEDS THEORY CONFERENCE" JULY ,1988 (Folder 18, Box 10)
  - "NEEDS THEORY CONFERENCE -INTRODUCTORY COMMENTS ,NEEDS THEORY AND CONFLICT RESOLUTION " JULY ,1988 (Folder 19, Box 10)
  - "COMPLIMENTS AND CONTEXTS FOR NEEDS THEORY :APPLIED SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY AND AN ECLECTIC MODEL OF CONFLICT " 1988 (Folder 20, Box 10)
  - "KNOWLEDGE: A SATISFIER ",YONA FRIEDMAN 1988 (Folder 21, Box 10)
  - "INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT IN HUMAN PERSPECTIVE ", JOHAN GALTUNG 1988 (Folder 22, Box 10)
  - "CONTRIBUTIONS OF NEEDS RESEARCH TO CONFLICT PREVENTION ", KATRIN GILLWALD 1988 - 1989 (Folder 1, Box 11)
  - "PROMOTING THE PEACEFUL RESOLUTION OF INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT CONTRIBUTIONS OF THE EMERGING FIELD OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION " ,JAMES H.LAUE 1988 - 1989 (Folder 2, Box 11)
  - "ON CONFLICT AND METAPHORS TOWARD AN EXTENDED RATIONALITY" 1988 - 1989 (Folder 3, Box 11)
  - "DECISION-MAKING PROCESSES: HOW DO THEY RESPOND TO HUMAN NEEDS ? ",WILLIAM R. POTAPCHUK 1988 - 1989 (Folder 4, Box 11)
  - "CONFLICTS ,CONFLICTS -RESOLUTION AND HUMAN NEEDS THEORIES :A FREE-WAY OR A DEAD END ?", RAMASHRAY ROY 1988 - 1989 (Folder 5, Box 11)
  - "RENEWAL AND RECONSTRUCTION IN INDIAN TRADITION :SARVODAYA AND SWADHYAYA " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 6, Box 11)
  - "POLITICAL VIOLENCE AND BASIC HUMAN NEEDS ",RICHARD E. RUBENSTEIN 1988 - 1989 (Folder 7, Box 11)
  - "THE BIOLOGICAL BASIS OF NEEDS IN WORLD SOCIETY: THE ULTIMATE MICRO-MACRO NEXUS ",DENNIS J.D SANDOLE 1988 - 1989 (Folder 8, Box 11)
  - "SELF-REFLEXITY AND FREEDOM AS BASIC HUMAN NEEDS: A THEORY OF CONFLICT RESOLUTION",JOSEPH A. SCIMECCA 1988 - 1989 (Folder 9, Box 11)
  - "EMOTIONS ,NEEDS,SELF AND CONTROL",PAUL SITES 1988 - 1989 (Folder 10, Box 11)
  - "NEWS CLIPPINGS " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 11, Box 11)
  - "ON THE NEED FOR CONFLICT PREVENTION " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 12, Box 11)
  - "RECEPTION " NOVEMBER 7,1989 (Folder 13, Box 11)
  - "A REGIONAL STRATEGY FROM STRATEGIC DETERRENCE TO PROBLEM SOLVING " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 14, Box 11)
  - "CONFLICT RESOLUTION AS A POLITICAL SYSTEM",WORKING PAPER 1988 - 1989 (Folder 15, Box 11)
  - "THE MESS CALLED PARTY POLITICS, ADVERSARIAL PARTY POLITICS VERSUS PROBLEM SOLVING " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 16, Box 11)
  - "THE LABOR TRADITION IN AUSTRALIAN FOREIGN POLICY " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 17, Box 11)
  - "CIVILIZATIONS IN CRISIS:FROM ADVERSARIAL TO PROBLEM SOLVING PROCESSES" 1988 - 1989 (Folder 18, Box 11)
  - "EXTERNAL AFFAIRS: A NOTE ABOUT OPEN DIPLOMACY " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 19, Box 11)
  - "CONFLICT PREVENTION AS A POLITICAL SYSTEM " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 20, Box 11)
  - "CONFLICT RESOLUTION AS A POLITICAL PHILOSOPHY " 1988 - 1989 (Folder 21, Box 11)
  - " THE CENTER FOR THE ANALYSIS OF CONFLICT" 1960 (Folder 1, Box 12)
  - " THE CENTER FOR THE ANALYSIS OF CONFLICT" 1968 (Folder 2, Box 12)
  - " DECISION-MAKING AS AN ART AND AS A SCIENCE" 1963 (Folder 3, Box 12)
  - "THE CENTRAL ROLE OF THEORY" 1965 (Folder 4, Box 12)
  - "CONFLICT AS A MEANS OF CHANGE" 1965 (Folder 5, Box 12)
  - "THE DRAFTING OF A MODEL REGIONAL ARRANGEMENT" 1966 (Folder 6, Box 12)
  - "THE ANALYSIS AND RESOLUTION OF CONFLICT" 1966 (Folder 7, Box 12)
  - " NONALIGNMENT AND CONTEMPORARY WORLD POLITICS" 1968 (Folder 8, Box 12)
  - "THE NATURE OF AGGRESSION AS REVEALED IN THE ATOMIC AGE" 1964 (Folder 9, Box 12)
  - " RECENT DEVELOPMENTS IN THEORY OF INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS" 1960 (Folder 10, Box 12)
  - " THE DECLINING RELEVANCE OF COERCION IN WORLD SOCIETY" 1960 (Folder 11, Box 12)
  - " MAJOR AND MINOR CONFERENCE PAPERS" 1970 (Folder 12, Box 12)
  - " MIDDLE-EAST IN 1960'S " 1960 (Folder 13, Box 12)
  - " RHODESIA-67, CYPRUS-66,INDONESIA-66 " 1960 - 1967 (Folder 14, Box 12)
  - " INTERNATIONAL SOCIOLOGY " (Folder 1, Box 13)
  - " INTERNATIONAL SOCIOLOGY " (Folder 2, Box 13)
  - " INTERNATIONAL SOCIOLOGY " (Folder 3, Box 13)
  - " INTERNATIONAL SOCIOLOGY " (Folder 4, Box 13)
  - "MEDIATION CONFERENCE " 1969 (Folder 5, Box 13)
  - " CENTRE EUROPEAN DE LA DOTATION CARNEGIE-GENEVA" 1970 (Folder 6, Box 13)